I've talked a lot about the different
benefits of omega-3 fats, but as I
always remind, something good isn't
going to be good in all instances. In
this case, we may be seeing a situation
where omega-3 fats may be a detriment.
Specifically, a study looking at the
role that omega-3 and omega6
polyunsaturated fats have inflammatory
bowel disease. But while this huge study
just released, it doesn't line up with
multiple other studies. And I think I
figured out why. So let's discuss what
we can take away from all this science.
In short, inflammatory bowel disease is
a in simplistic language misfiring of
immune system all along the
gastrointestinal system from the mouth
all the way to the anus. Now Crohn's
disease, a subset of inflammatory bowel
disease, is the full thing. Inflammation
anywhere in the gastrointestinal system.
Ulcerative colitis is another subset of
IBD or inflammatory bowel disease and it
only affects the colon and the rectum.
Now we'll discuss both in relation to
this study. If we take samples of the
intestinal tract from people with IBD,
Crohn's or ulcerative colitis, and we
look at the amount of activity by
specific functional proteins within the
cells of the intestine, we'd see that
people with IBD have a reproducibly
high activity of a protein called RXR
alpha or retinoid X receptor alpha. Why
does that matter? Because in short more
RXR alpha activity is linked to more
inflammation especially as it's highly
active in cells of the intestines called
panith cells. These are specialized
immune supporting cells in the
intestines and this is where the
polyunsaturated fats like omega-3s come
in. Okay. So we know that inflammatory
bowel disease has greater activity of
this RXR alpha protein in immune
adjacent cells called panda cells. From
there we as in scientists can use a
microscope technique called fret which
allows us to quantify the proximity of
the RXR alpha protein to different fats
in this instance. So this gives us a
clue as to which fats are interacting
with this protein heavily tied to
inflammation. The fats are listed on the
bottom. So don't worry, I'll explain
them. The higher the bars, the closer
the fat is to the RXR alpha protein,
indicating that it might bind to it and
change its activity. So, we're comparing
against baseline, so called a vehicle.
And the PA there is a saturated fat. The
OA is a monounsaturated fat. Both don't
get close to the protein. However, an
omega-6 polyunsaturated fat and multiple
omega-3 fats are in close close
proximity. So in fact when exposing
cells to polyunsaturated fats here then
measuring if RX binds to a gene heavily
implicated in intestinal inflammation
CX1
we see RXR alpha is bound more likely
increasing its production from gene to
functional inflammatory protein. This
all means, including some experiments
that I didn't show you, that
polyunsaturated fats exclusively out of
other fats bind RXR alpha and increase
its activity in IBD. So that's the basic
rationale, but the study focused on a
lot of mechanisms. So it used mice for
many of its experiments except for the
initial discovery of RXR alpha activity
in IBD. The researchers then
strengthened their case by pointing out
that clinical studies giving high doses
of omega-3 polyunsaturated fats do not
show improvement in Crohn's disease. And
they're right. The studies cited show no
benefit. Now, this challenges the notion
that omega-3s are anti-inflammatory in
every context. Now, I'll return to the
clinical data shortly because there's
some uh more to know there that isn't
mentioned in the study. Still, even with
this mechanistic evidence and the
clinical evidence, which carries more
weight, it's puzzling to find other
studies that indicate omega-3 fats
actually track with reduced risk of
inflammatory bowel disease. In fact, in
long-term studies, uh, over decades
where people's nutrition is tracked
every few years to keep a pulse on their
intake and their blood values, a greater
omega-3 consumption relative to omega6
indicates reduced risk of ulcerative
colitis. A similar story for this study
shown here transformed based on the
original data. You see that the risk of
Crohn's disease reduced with greater
consumption of omega-3, so specifically
DHA or dosahexoninoic acid. The only
statistically significant reduced risk
relationship was shown at the highest
intakes. My point here being that this
study that we've been focused on is not
consistent with the literature. So why
is that? Well, there's two reasons which
really get to some important nuances
that make this clear to anyone afraid of
developing inflammatory bowel disease.
Now, if you're interested in learning
more about the mechanisms of omega-3s
and inflammatory bowel disease, or you
want to know more about the clinical
data, then check out my extended
analysis, which belongs to the Physionic
Insiders, which is my premium research
platform. You also get articles that
come along with the videos, including
this one, obviously. You get a private
podcast. You get one paragraph
summaries. You get a private email list
where you get everything sent to you
every week. and you get much more like
the stuff that I've got covered right
here. If you're interested, then check
out the Physionic Insiders using the
link in the description. See you there.
One, I mentioned I wanted to return to
this clinical evidence because the
researchers point to a lack of a benefit
from highdose omega-3 fats in a
randomized control trial. However,
that's not what they are showing in
their own study, right? We're not
talking about a lack of an effect. We're
talking about omega-3s causing
inflammatory bowel disease, not that
it's neutral. So, the use of this study
as a clinical evidence I find rather
flimsy to be honest with you. Then, when
we look at the high quality meta
analyses, basically analyses including
many studies, you'll find some slightly
different results. So, technically that
same clinical study was included in this
meta analysis. And it's true. If you
focus in on just that study and a
sibling study, you'd confirm that
omega-3 supplementation offers no
benefit and in fact can raise the risk
of diarrhea and upset stomach in people
with Crohn's disease. Yet, if you look
at all the studies, including the ones
that we just discussed, there is an
effect of omega-3 consumption, a reduced
risk of inflammatory event in people
with Crohn's disease in remission. So
the point here is that most of the
evidence doesn't indicate inflammatory
harm of omega-3 consumption, generally
neutral or even positive. That brings us
to number two, which is a context where
omega-3s could be harmful. A context
where all the previous research is true
and this new research is also true. The
associative studies that I pointed out
earlier were not in people with IBD. So,
it's possible that if you don't have
IBD, you are slightly less likely to get
it if you consume omega-3s. On the other
hand, people with IBD might consider
reducing their polyunsaturated fat
consumption, omega-3 and omega 6,
slightly if they are consistently
experiencing symptoms. Keep in mind that
the clinical data points to neutral or
positive effects of omega-3. So could
there be another variable necessary that
creates a foundation for polyunsaturated
fats to be a negative?
Possibly because the main study
primarily looked at polyunsaturated fat
consumption in the context of a poor
diet, meaning higher total fat, higher
calories, western diet. It even provided
evidence that without this background,
there don't seem to be any inflammatory
issues. So, this would suggest that if
you don't have IBD, don't worry about
any of this based on the evidence that
we have. If you do deal with IBD, but
you consume a lower fat diet, there's
probably also low concern of consuming
some proportion of that fat as omega-3s.
However, if you suffer from IBD and your
diet is a mixture of sugars, high
polyunsaturated fats, unregulated intake
of food, eating ultrarocessed foods on a
regular basis, and then the additional
supplementation, or consumption of a
whole or any polyunsaturated fat, omega6
or omega-3, then it may trigger greater
inflammation through this RXR alpha
binding. As you can see, there's a lot
of nuance that allows all the evidence
to exist and not contradict. But also
keep in mind that there's really isn't a
ton of evidence on some of these
intricacies. So, there's plenty of room
there to amend as more data releases.
And because of how loose the
interpretation is here, it may be
worthwhile if you have IBD to take stock
of your flare-ups and look at your diet.
Is it particularly heavy in omega6 and
omega-3 fats? If so, you may be
particularly pl pr prone to this
mechanism through RXR alpha. In the end,
the one thing I know for certain is that
this next video is not inflammatory in
the least. So, you're safe to click on
it. I hope this was informative and I
hope to catch you in the next one. Bye.